Finding Aid for Omega Psi Phi Fraternity, Sigma Rho Chapter Records, 1964-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Omega Psi Phi Fraternity, Sigma Rho Chapter Records 1964-1997
Omega Psi Phi Fraternity. Sigma Rho Chapter (Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti, Mich.)
1 linear ft.
University of Michigan chapter of African-American fraternity; includes administrative records and topical files relating to the activities of the fraternity
9949 Bd 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from Omega Psi Phi, Sigma Rho chapter, through Victor Turner in 1999. (Donor no. 8836 )
The record group is open for research.
Omega Psi Phi, an African-American fraternity, was founded on the principles of "manhood, scholarship, perseverance, and uplift" on November 11, 1911 at Howard University by four undergraduate men. Today, the fraternity consists of graduate and undergraduate chapters located across the United States. Sigma Rho, the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti graduate chapter, was founded in 1964. Throughout its existence, the organization interacted with local undergraduates. These undergraduates were inducted into the Lampados Club, an informal undergraduate chapter within Sigma Rho, until the 1990 reinstatement of a formal undergraduate Phi chapter at the University of Michigan.
Sigma Rho was primarily a social/community service organization. In compliance with national fraternal mandates, members organized dances, golf tournaments, and talent shows to raise money to provide local high-schoolers with college scholarships. The group also gave generous financial support to the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and the United Negro College Fund, and as a local service, compiled a directory of Black Businesses and Organizations in the Washtenaw County area.
The Omega Psi Phi, Sigma Rho chapter records are arranged in two series: Administrative and Topical Records. These illustrate the positive impact that gifts of time and money given by social/community service organizations have upon their local communities.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Societies, etc.; Omega Psi Phi Fraternity. Sigma Rho Chapter (Ann Arbor- Ypsilanti, Mich.)
- Administrative, 1964-1997
  The Administrative series documents the internal organization of Sigma Rho, and contains material such as the minutes of the chapter meetings, and the committee reports from 1964 to 1997. Also included are scattered minutes of the Omega Psi Phi district and national meetings. Several summaries of 10th district meetings, of which Sigma Rho was a part, are included. The administrative series also contains some minutes from the meetings of the Supreme Council, Omega Psi Phi's national government, and the Grand Conclave, the annual voluntary gathering of Omega Psi Phi members. Also included are the financial records, bylaws, membership rosters, and scattered correspondence between Sigma Rho, its members, and the national fraternal government.
  - Minutes
    - Sigma Rho, 1964-1997, 14 folders (Box 1)
      (lacking 1983, 1984, and 1995
    - 10th District, 1977, 1981, 1988-1994, 1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Supreme Council, 1979, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Grand Conclave, 1988, 1990, 1994, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, 1985, 1986, 1989, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Finances
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1997 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1997 (Box 1)
  - Membership, 1964, 1987-1988, 1990, 1991, 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
- Topical, 1966-1997
  The Topical series consists primarily of material generated by the charitable and social activities of Sigma Rho. It contains documentation of Sigma Rho's relationship with undergraduate fraternity members. Also included in the series are internal Omega Psi Phi publications, such as national and district newsletters, and external publications, such as newsclippings.
  - Achievement Week/Founders, 1982, 1989, 1991-1993, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Art Fair, 1986, 1989, 1991, 1992, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
  - Assault on Illiteracy, 1991, 1992, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Directory of Black Organizations and Businesses, 1984, 1992, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Essay/Scholarship Contests, 1979, 1988-1993, 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Fall Dance, 1989, 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Fall Golf Scramble, 1994, 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Friendship Open, 1990-1997 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, scattered dates (Box 1)
  - Publications, 1989-1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Reclamation and Retention, 1989-1992, 1994, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Social Action Committee, 1986, 1989, 1990, 1992, 1994, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Talent Hunt, 1966-1970, 1976, 1981, 1989, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate Relations, 1985, 1990, 2 folders (Box 1)